<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Pelayo Arbues peer-reviewed on</title><link>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/tags/peer-reviewed/</link><description> Unglamorous Data Science management</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://pelayoarbues.github.io/tags/peer-reviewed/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>A Stochastic Frontier Analysis Approach for Estimating Energy Demand and Efficiency in the Transport Sector of Latin America and the Caribbean</title><link>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/research/A-Stochastic-Frontier-Analysis-Approach-for-Estimating-Energy-Demand/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/research/A-Stochastic-Frontier-Analysis-Approach-for-Estimating-Energy-Demand/</guid><description>&lt;p>Authors: Manuel Llorca, José Baños, José Somoza, Pelayo Arbués&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>In this paper, a stochastic frontier analysis approach is applied to estimate energy demand functions in the transport sector. This approach allows us to obtain energy efficiency measures at country level that are a robust alternative to the energy intensity indicators commonly used for international comparisons. A transitive multilateral price index is constructed for aggregating the diverse energy components employed in the sector. Due to the likely unobserved heterogeneity among countries, the use of a random parameters model is proposed to accommodate these differences and to obtain different income and price elasticities per country. The estimated model is compared with alternative approaches of addressing this issue such as latent class, true fixed effects or true random effects models. This study is the first to use a random parameters stochastic frontier approach in the estimation of energy demand functions. The proposed procedure is applied to Latin America and the Caribbean, where the transport sector represents a large share of total energy consumption.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>DOI:&lt;/strong> 
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.5547/01956574.38.5.mllo" rel="noopener">https://doi.org/10.5547/01956574.38.5.mllo&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Determinants of ground transport modal choice in long-distance trips in Spain</title><link>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/research/Determinants-of-ground-transport-modal-choice-in-long-distance-trips-in-Spain/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/research/Determinants-of-ground-transport-modal-choice-in-long-distance-trips-in-Spain/</guid><description>&lt;p>Authors: Pelayo Arbués, José F. Baños, Matías Mayor&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>In transport economics, modeling modal choice is a fundamental key for policy makers try-ing to improve the sustainability of transportation systems. However, existing empiricalliterature has focused on short-distance travel within urban systems. This paper con-tributes to the limited number of investigations on mode choice in medium- andlong-distance travel. The main objective of this research is to study the impacts ofsocio-demographic and economic variables, land-use features and trip attributes onlong-distance travel mode choice. Using data from 2007 Spanish National MobilitySurvey we apply a multilevel multinomial logit model that accounts for the potential prob-lem of spatial heterogeneity in order to explain long-distance travel mode choice. Thisapproach permits us to compute how the probability of choosing among private car, busand train varies depending on the traveler spatial location at regional level. Results indicatethat travelers characteristics, trip features, cost of usage of transport modes and geograph-ical variables have significant impacts on long-distance mode choice.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>DOI:&lt;/strong>
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tra.2015.06.010" rel="noopener">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tra.2015.06.010&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The spatial productivity of transportation infrastructure</title><link>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/research/The-spatial-productivity-of-transportation-infrastructure/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/research/The-spatial-productivity-of-transportation-infrastructure/</guid><description>&lt;p>Authors: Pelayo Arbués, José F. Baños, Matías Mayor, Patricia Suárez&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Transportation infrastructure services may cause an impact on the economy of the region in which they are located and, additionally, they are likely to have an impact on other regions. This effect has been labeled the spillover effect. In this study, the existence of direct and spillover effects of road, railway, airport and seaport infrastructure projects is tested by estimating a production function. Together with this primary objective, two common concerns in the literature are addressed: the lack of theoretical foundations for spatial econometrics models and the likely endogenous relationship between transport infrastructure and economic development. The estimated production function takes the form of a Spatial Durbin Model and is estimated using panel data from the 47 peninsular Spanish provinces by alternatively applying a Maximum Likelihood estimator and Instrumental Variables/Generalized Method of Moments estimators. According to the estimates, road transport infrastructure positively affects the output of the region in which the infrastructure is located and its neighboring provinces, while the remaining modes of transportation projects cause no significant impacts on average.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>DOI:&lt;/strong>
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tra.2015.03.010" rel="noopener">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tra.2015.03.010&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A dynamic approach to road freight flows modeling in Spain</title><link>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/research/A-dynamic-approach-to-road-freight-flows-modeling-in-Spain/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/research/A-dynamic-approach-to-road-freight-flows-modeling-in-Spain/</guid><description>&lt;p>Authors: Pelayo Arbués, José F. Baños&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>This paper presents an innovative approach to analyzing road vehicle freight traffic that uses a dynamic panel data specification derived from a gravity model. This dynamic approach, which has recently been employed in international goods trade models in lieu of the traditional static specification, is applied to the case of Spain using data for the countrys 15 NUTS-3 regions between 1999 and 2009. Using the system general method of moments approach, we obtained significant evidence that the flow of vehicles carrying commodities by road has a strong persistence effect when controlling for unobserved heterogeneity. We also found that the quality of road transport infrastructure has a significant impact on vehicle trips. According to our findings, we suggest that this type of specification be employed in distribution models in which fixed effects and lags of the dependent variable are included to account for unobserved heterogeneity and persistence effects, respectively.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>DOI:&lt;/strong>
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11116-015-9590-5" rel="noopener">https://doi.org/10.1007/s11116-015-9590-5&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>