<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Pelayo Arbues Permanent Note on</title><link>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/tags/permanent-note/</link><description> Unglamorous Data Science management</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://pelayoarbues.github.io/tags/permanent-note/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>202301301801 - Data teamwork as a transport service</title><link>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/notes/202301301801-Data-teamwork-as-a-transport-service/</link><pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/notes/202301301801-Data-teamwork-as-a-transport-service/</guid><description>&lt;p>Long time ago, I was a transport economics guy. The other day I was thinking about the different existent data roles. I came up with the following metaphors:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Data platform builds the roads, harbours, railroads and airports&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Data Engineering do the heavy transport&lt;/li>
&lt;li>DS makes the last mile&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>This creates some ego problems. DS think they do all the work. Data Engineering and Data platform folks are really far away from the customers, don&amp;rsquo;t get enough credit and feel disconnected from the business.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>202301301801 - Write well to solve problems</title><link>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/notes/202301301801-Write-well-to-solve-problems/</link><pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/notes/202301301801-Write-well-to-solve-problems/</guid><description>&lt;p>According to
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/paulg/status/1460660779309572105?s=20&amp;amp;t=7dRAEzZ4YbsG8TvkblNYoA" rel="noopener">Paul Graham&lt;/a>, in order to write well, one must read well. Similarly, to think well, particularly when dealing with ill-defined problems, one must write.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve been consistently writing for some time now. I take notes on the books I read and then process them by applying lessons I&amp;rsquo;ve learned from various sources, particularly from &amp;ldquo;How to Take Smart Notes&amp;rdquo;. From the connections between these ideas, I generate new texts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I also write meeting minutes to keep a record of the decisions made and the actions to be taken for those who weren&amp;rsquo;t present at the meeting, and to identify the
&lt;a href="https://medium.com/@mmamet/directly-responsible-individuals-f5009f465da4" rel="noopener">Directly Responsible Individual&lt;/a> who is responsible for carrying out those tasks.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Additionally, I write process documentation to standardize our team&amp;rsquo;s expectations on a project.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Furthermore, I write about problems that I encounter and for which I have yet to find a solution. When attempting to tackle these problems, I write my thought process down.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I intend to make more of these writings public. While newsletters are currently trending, I prefer to create a digital garden for now. Anyone who wishes to do so can subscribe to the RSS feed, observe my learning process in real-time, and participate in discussions.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>202211141711 - Short term and long term metrics</title><link>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/notes/202211141711-Short-term-and-long-term-metrics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/notes/202211141711-Short-term-and-long-term-metrics/</guid><description>&lt;p>Optimising the wrong metrics might make you win the finite game, but lose the infinite one. Beware what you chase.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>James P. Carse wrote that ==there are two kinds of games in life: finite and infinite. A finite game is played to win; there are clear victors and losers. An infinite game is played to keep playing; the goal is to maximize winning across all participants. Debate is a finite game. Marriage is an infinite game. The midterm elections are finite games. American democracy is an infinite game.== A great deal of unnecessary suffering in the world comes from not knowing the difference. A bad fight can destroy a marriage. A challenged election can destabilize a democracy. In baseball, winning the World Series is a finite game, while growing the popularity of Major League Baseball is an infinite game. What happened, I think, is that baseball’s finite game was solved so completely in such a way that the infinite game was lost.
&lt;a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/newsletters/archive/2022/10/sabermetrics-analytics-ruined-baseball-sports-music-film/671924/" rel="noopener">What moneyball has done to American culture&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></description></item><item><title>202211102211 - Team size trade-off. Coordination costs Vs collective intelligence</title><link>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/notes/202211102211-Team-size-trade-off.-Coordination-costs-Vs-collective-intelligence/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/notes/202211102211-Team-size-trade-off.-Coordination-costs-Vs-collective-intelligence/</guid><description>&lt;p>Many of us have faced this tradeoff. As our team grows bigger, coordination costs and waste rise. At the same time, the potential collective intelligence of the group also increases. Our job as managers is to keep unproductive tasks under control while leveraging a hive of minds. This post by Ethan Mollick provides some research on how to do it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;a href="https://oneusefulthing.substack.com/p/the-problem-of-management-in-two?sd=pf" rel="noopener">The problem of management&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>202210241310 - Make'em talk with prototypes</title><link>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/notes/202210241310-Makeem-talk-with-prototypes/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/notes/202210241310-Makeem-talk-with-prototypes/</guid><description>&lt;p>Data product projects can be challenging to execute as stakeholder requirements are often vague and undefined. In my experience, upfront design of data products can be difficult since the data team may not have the necessary context to create an appropriate solution.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Having numerous meetings to design the first version is often ineffective. However, creating a prototype can be a productive and efficient method of encouraging people to discuss their requirements. Through the creation of a prototype, stakeholders can see, touch and use a tangible representation of the product, and give feedback on its functionality.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Initially, stakeholders may say that the prototype is not what they need and provide further details on the desired functionality, which the data team can use to improve the prototype.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It is essential to inform the data team that some of the prototype materials may not be used, or may end up as appendices in a document. However, prototypes remain one of the most efficient ways of understanding what customers need in a data product.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>While some may view this as an inefficient method of working, it is a crucial way to comprehend the true requirements of customers and design a data product that meets their needs.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>202210172210 - Bayesian reasoning</title><link>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/notes/202210172210-Bayesian-reasoning/</link><pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/notes/202210172210-Bayesian-reasoning/</guid><description>&lt;p>Bayesian-style belief updating involves changing probabilistic beliefs in response to evidence. Bayes&amp;rsquo; rule is the theorem that indicates how much we should change our minds when we learn a new fact or observe new evidence
&lt;a href="https://arbital.com/p/bayes_rule/?l=1zq" rel="noopener">Arbital&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bayes&amp;rsquo; rule also tells us how strong a piece of evidence has to be in order to support a given hypothesis. Extraordinary claims require extraordinary evidence. The theorem lets us see whether a piece of evidence is sufficient, or insufficient, to drive the probability of a hypothesis to over 50%. That is: an &amp;ldquo;
&lt;a href="https://arbital.com/p/extraordinary_claims/" rel="noopener">extraordinary claim&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo; is one with a low 
&lt;a href="https://arbital.com/p/prior_probability/" rel="noopener">prior probability&lt;/a> in advance of considering the evidence, and &amp;ldquo;extraordinary evidence&amp;rdquo; is evidence with an extreme 
&lt;a href="https://arbital.com/p/relative_likelihood/" rel="noopener">likelihood ratio&lt;/a> favoring the claim over its alternatives.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A corollary to 
&lt;a href="https://arbital.com/p/bayes_extraordinary_claims/" rel="noopener">extraordinary claims require extraordinary evidence&lt;/a> is &amp;ldquo;ordinary claims require only ordinary evidence&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>202210172210 - Rationalism takes us closer to the truth</title><link>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/notes/202210172210-Rationality-takes-us-closer-to-the-truth/</link><pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/notes/202210172210-Rationality-takes-us-closer-to-the-truth/</guid><description>&lt;p>Rationality involves the process of systematically evaluating and revising our beliefs based on available evidence to create a more accurate understanding of reality. It is an ongoing process that allows us to refine our understanding of the world and better align our beliefs with the actual state of affairs. When our beliefs accurately map onto reality, we are better equipped to make informed decisions and take appropriate actions to achieve our goals.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The value of rationality lies in its ability to help us avoid common cognitive biases that can lead to inaccurate beliefs and poor decision-making. By using evidence-based reasoning and critical thinking, rationality enables us to evaluate information in a systematic and objective way. We can weigh the evidence for and against a particular belief, and use that information to adjust our understanding of the world.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The benefits of rationality extend beyond just the realm of decision-making. A more accurate understanding of reality can help us better appreciate the world around us, and develop a more nuanced and sophisticated view of the world. By adopting a rational approach to our beliefs, we can expand our horizons, challenge our assumptions, and become more informed and engaged members of society.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In summary, rationality is a powerful tool for creating a more accurate understanding of the world, enabling better decision-making, and achieving our goals. By continuously evaluating and revising our beliefs, we can develop a more nuanced and sophisticated view of the world, while avoiding the pitfalls of cognitive biases and subjective thinking.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/RcZCwxFiZzE6X7nsv/what-do-we-mean-by-rationality-1" rel="noopener">What Do We Mean By Rationality - LessWrong&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Rational Company</title><link>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/writing/The-Rational-Company/</link><pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/writing/The-Rational-Company/</guid><description>&lt;p>In the past years many companies have claimed to be adopting processes that allows them to be more intensively driven by data. Although most of these companies focus on the technology and tools used, we could assume that what they are trying to do is to improve their decision making processes. We could say that they try to become rational.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Rationality is about more than just forming true beliefs – it&amp;rsquo;s also about making decisions that help you achieve your goals. Decision making is the ability to make sound, rational decisions based on the available information. This process begins with understanding what it is that the company wants to achieve – its north star goal. Once this is clear, the company can start collecting relevant data and expertise to inform its decisions. Finally, creating a culture of lifelong learning will ensure that the company continues to get better at making decisions over time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Better decision making might require open minded profesionals, eager to adopt a bayesian-style culture where prior beliefs are constantly updated by new facts and evidence. Being willing to change our minds when new evidence arises is important for making smart decisions – after all, if we’re always sticking to our original ideas, chances are we won’t be taking advantage of all the potential options out there. All of these qualities together – being open-minded and thinking critically about information, as well as being willing to alter our beliefs in light of new data – make for better decision making overall.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the absence of enough data, beliefs based on experience and expert knowledge can provide a competitive advantage. important it is for companies to have experts on their team who can rely on intuition and experience when making decisions based on insufficient information.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Strategies purely based on mathematical rationality without a qualitative understanding of decision-making and human behaviour tend to underperform.&lt;/strong>
&lt;a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/introduction-to-decision-intelligence-5d147ddab767" rel="noopener">What is Decision Intelligence#The trouble with your brain&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Blindly trusting data and statistics without verifying their validity is also a risk, as it could lead to incorrect decisions being made. By using Bayesian reasoning techniques, businesses can mitigate these risks and optimise their operations accordingly.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>202210141310 - Data is not objective</title><link>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/notes/202210141310-Data-is-not-objective/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/notes/202210141310-Data-is-not-objective/</guid><description>&lt;p>Data is not objective. Although it may seem like a neutral representation of reality, the truth is that data is always obtained through some sort of instrument or technique that imposes a particular structure to the information we aim to study. Furthermore, we often transform data and use models to search for patterns, which can further shape our understanding of the information. I like this
&lt;a href="https://www.datanalytics.com/2021/01/21/mas-sobre-el-mito-de-la-objetividad-especialmente-la-data-driven/" rel="noopener">post on the topic by Carlos Gil Bellosta&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>While the concept of being data-driven can be appealing, it&amp;rsquo;s important to remember that this approach does not necessarily uncover absolute truths or a complete understanding of how the world operates. Our flawed human brains act as lenses through which we view and interpret data, and our biases and limitations can affect the way we interpret information.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s crucial to approach data analysis with a critical eye and an awareness of potential biases, limitations, and assumptions. Rather than assuming that data alone can provide a complete picture of reality, we must continually question and refine our understanding of the world through ongoing inquiry and exploration.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>202210142200 - Ideal data to solve a problem</title><link>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/notes/202210142200-Ideal-data-to-solve-a-problem/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/notes/202210142200-Ideal-data-to-solve-a-problem/</guid><description>&lt;p>My favourite stage at the DS process is thinking about what data would be ideal to solve a particular problem.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is an abstract and theoretical moment when you can be as creative as you want. Forget about data silos, infrastructure problems or data quality issues. It is a wishlist. You can order whatever you want.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I like doing this process in isolation, just letting my mind wander and flow. In my opinion, this is probably one of the most creative and fun parts of the project because you have no constraints, except your own knowledge about your sector or the process at stake. And that&amp;rsquo;s is also another reason that this is a fabulous moment as it allows you to test your own knowledge.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But at some point I will get stuck and that&amp;rsquo;s when I go into the next step of this early stage of a project. Truth is that most of our work is optimization, in many cases we aim to make some processes more automatic so it is likely that there is someone who has been working in that task before you arrived to the organization. So at this point you go and talk to people, sometimes people you have never heard of if you are in a big company. And it is also a quite remarkable moment in the project, because you will be learning more about your domain and you start gazing the purpose of your work: make someone&amp;rsquo;s life a bit better so that the business machine keeps oiled and running.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Don&amp;rsquo;t fool yourself, talking to people and trying to extract information of how they work usually takes way longer than you thought. If you are facing a complicated project you should be starting to think how to make this new long term relationship as successful as possible. And probably is by keeping them informed about your advances and frustrations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Before going deeper and start reading scientific papers and blog posts by companies who have faced similar challenges, I like chatting to my colleagues. At this point you are usually quite confident about what the ideal data looks like, as you have devoted some hours of your time to think about the problem. However, every time that I do this I find that my colleague points to an hole in my ideal dataset and proposes something new and smart.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Now read papers, blogs and so on with a critical mindselt. Can you spot the excellence in the data they are using? Can you spot the data challenges they might be facing? Try to read between the lines in that tech giant post that brag about how good they are solving the challenge you are facing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The final step would be to create a matrix that allows us to map potential and effort required of all those pieces of data in your wishlist.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>2202205171305 - Reversible and irreversible decision making</title><link>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/notes/202205171305-Reversible-and-irreversible-decision-making/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/notes/202205171305-Reversible-and-irreversible-decision-making/</guid><description>&lt;p>Before making a decision we should analyse it and meta-decide whether that decision is reversible or not irreversible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It is a mental model
&lt;a
rel="noopener" class="internal-link broken"
data-src="#ZgotmplZ">proposed by Bezos at Amazon&lt;/a> to know when a decision should be made quickly or if a deeper analysis is needed.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Many irreversible decisions are made irrationally driven by necessity [having a sense of being in control of your life](
&lt;a href="https://www.elconfidencial.com/cultura/2022-05-01/dejar-trabajo-divorciarte-gran-renuncia_3416531/" rel="noopener">Quitting your job is the new divorcing your partner at 40 and becoming a &amp;lsquo;runner&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a>).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>202202052202 - Different managerial styles</title><link>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/notes/202202052202-Different-managerial-styles/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/notes/202202052202-Different-managerial-styles/</guid><description>&lt;p>Effective management requires the use of different managerial styles to suit different situations and team members. The success of a manager often depends on their ability to adapt their approach to the needs and strengths of their team.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When it comes to data science, the need for different managerial styles is even more pronounced. Data science is a rapidly evolving field that attracts professionals from a wide range of backgrounds, including computer science, statistics, mathematics, engineering, and many more. As a result, data science teams are often highly diverse, with team members possessing a wide range of skills, expertise, and personalities.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One reason for the need for different managerial styles is that each team member is unique, with their own personality, strengths, and weaknesses. A good manager recognizes these individual differences and tailors their approach to suit each person. For example, some team members may thrive on autonomy and require minimal supervision, while others may need more guidance and direction.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another reason for the need for different managerial styles is that different situations call for different approaches. For instance, a crisis situation may require a more directive, hands-on approach from the manager, while a routine task may require a more hands-off approach.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Furthermore, different styles of management can be more effective in different organizational cultures. For instance, a highly collaborative, team-oriented culture may require a more participative, democratic leadership style, while a more hierarchical, top-down culture may benefit from a more directive leadership style.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Ultimately, the need for different managerial styles stems from the fact that no two situations, teams, or team members are exactly alike. Effective managers are those who are able to recognize these differences and adapt their approach accordingly. They are able to flex their leadership style to fit the needs of the situation and the team, and to use a variety of management techniques to motivate, engage, and support their team members. By doing so, they are able to build strong, high-performing teams that can achieve their goals and meet the needs of the organization.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>202202052202 - Understanding low level data science</title><link>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/notes/202202052202-Understanding-low-level-data-science/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/notes/202202052202-Understanding-low-level-data-science/</guid><description>&lt;p>Having a deep understanding of the low-level details of data science techniques can be highly beneficial for data professionals in several ways.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Firstly, it allows them to have a deeper understanding of the underlying principles and assumptions of the techniques they are using. This understanding enables them to choose the right tool for the job and to adapt the technique to the specific context they are working on. For instance I majored in spatial econometrics, a set of techniques to deal with spatial autocorrelation. I have not been able to use them at scale but they provide me the intuition to do spatial feature engineering in some of the projects I worked.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Secondly, a deeper understanding of low-level details allows data scientists to break down complex problems into smaller, more manageable pieces. This helps them to identify the most relevant parts of a technique for their specific use case and to adapt it as necessary. For example, having an understanding of the inner workings of deep learning models can help a data scientist to identify the most relevant layers and parameters for a specific project.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thirdly, having a deep understanding of data science techniques helps data professionals to avoid becoming &amp;ldquo;library practitioners&amp;rdquo; who rely solely on pre-existing libraries and packages without much thought. While libraries can be useful, they are not always a perfect fit for every use case. A deep understanding of the underlying principles and assumptions of a technique can help a data scientist to make informed decisions about when and how to use libraries, and to adapt them to their specific needs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, it is important to note that having a deep understanding of data science techniques is not a guarantee of success. It is important to ensure that these skills are aligned with the specific needs and goals of a project or organization. For instance, being an expert in deep learning may not be useful in a company that does not use this technology. Ultimately, the key is to strike a balance between depth of knowledge and relevance to the specific context in which a data professional operates.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>202202021502 - Mentoring as a form of leverage</title><link>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/notes/202202021502-Mentoring-as-a-form-of-leverage/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/notes/202202021502-Mentoring-as-a-form-of-leverage/</guid><description>&lt;p>The productivity of a developer or data scientist is typically measured by the impact produced per hour invested. While a junior developer may be able to produce linear impact with their hours spent on a task, a senior developer can create exponential impact by mentoring junior team members as explained in
&lt;a href="https://www.susanshu.com/entry-level-to-senior-developer-multiplier" rel="noopener">From entry level to senior+ developer - Multiply impact with developer leverage&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>By taking the time to teach an entry-level colleague, the senior person can not only reduce the development time of the junior, but also impart their knowledge and expertise to the junior. This has the added benefit of reducing the senior person&amp;rsquo;s own workload, freeing them up to work on tasks that only they can do, while the junior can take care of maintenance or evolution.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Moreover, mentoring helps to spread the senior person&amp;rsquo;s skills and knowledge throughout the team or organization, creating a more robust and resilient team that can handle complex challenges more effectively. Mentoring can also create a positive feedback loop, where junior team members become more skilled and confident, leading to even greater impact and productivity for the entire team.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In short, mentoring is a highly effective way for senior developers or data scientists to create leverage and have a greater impact beyond their own work. By sharing their expertise with junior team members, they can create exponential impact, reduce their own workload, and contribute to the development of a more skilled and effective team.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>202202011102 - By-products of multiple processes</title><link>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/notes/202202011102-By-products-of-multiple-processes/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/notes/202202011102-By-products-of-multiple-processes/</guid><description>&lt;p>In the chemistry industry, &amp;ldquo;Verbund&amp;rdquo; refers to an integrated production process where by-products from one process are used as inputs in another process, resulting in a more efficient and sustainable overall system.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In data science, a similar concept can be applied to the use of by-products from one analysis or modeling process as inputs for another analysis or modeling process, leading to a more efficient and effective overall data science workflow. For example, the output of one machine learning model can be used as input for another model, or data generated as a by-product of one analysis can be repurposed for another analysis.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This approach can help reduce data waste, increase efficiency, and improve overall data-driven decision-making. In this way you may create a network of intertwined processes. It reminds me of the way stitch fix presented the
&lt;a href="https://cultivating-algos.stitchfix.com/" rel="noopener">organic connection of its projects&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>202202011102 - Career advice on skill acquisition</title><link>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/notes/202202011102-Career-advice-on-skill-acquisition/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pelayoarbues.github.io/notes/202202011102-Career-advice-on-skill-acquisition/</guid><description>&lt;p>As a data professional, one optimal career strategy is to diversify your skill set and strive to become proficient in multiple areas. Instead of focusing solely on becoming a top 10% expert in one skill, aim to become a top 25% expert in at least three different skills.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For example, as a data professional, you could strive to become a top 25% expert in machine learning engineering, data engineering, and public speaking. By doing so, you can increase your value and versatility to potential employers or clients.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>By doing so, you can increase your value and versatility to potential employers or clients, making you a more attractive candidate for a wider range of roles and projects. Having expertise in multiple areas can also make you better equipped to handle complex, interdisciplinary challenges and solve problems that require a range of skills and perspectives.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Moreover, diversifying your skill set can help you stay adaptable and relevant as technology and industries continue to evolve. By continuously learning and applying new tools and techniques, you can avoid becoming obsolete in a single field and remain competitive in the job market.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, it&amp;rsquo;s important to strike a balance between diversifying your skill set and maintaining depth of knowledge in your core areas of expertise. Don&amp;rsquo;t spread yourself too thin or sacrifice your in-depth understanding of your field. Instead, focus on cultivating a broad range of skills that complement and enhance your existing expertise, making you a more valuable and adaptable data professional in the long term.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Great sources for this discussion are
&lt;a href="https://dilbertblog.typepad.com/the_dilbert_blog/2007/07/career-advice.html" rel="noopener">Career Advice&lt;/a> and
&lt;a href="https://unchartedterritories.tomaspueyo.com/p/how-to-become-the-best-in-the-world" rel="noopener">How to Become the Best in the World at Something&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>